What's up everybody?
>> Awesome. Uh thought before we uh
officially got rolling, I'd uh kind of
address a few things. I certainly didn't
want to miss it. And so first, a couple
of uh empty seats over to my right and
uh was absolutely bummed uh to hear
about the Washington Post uh sports
section. So some of the guys Barry and
Taan and Tom like true pros and uh along
with everyone else I met there uh their
presence is missed. So second, I would
like to also acknowledge kind of the
organization lost a legend in Sunny
Jurgensson and one of the great
ambassadors for us to wear the Burgundy
and Gold. And additionally wanted to
send condolences to cornerback Barry
Wilburn's family. And we've got great
alumni here and a great alumni base men
who have proudly set the standard here.
And as a steward for this era of
Washington football, like man, can I
tell you how much I appreciate that and
how much goes into setting those kind of
standards. And then third, one of the mo
the most tremendous people I know you've
had a chance to cover is Bobby Wagner.
And we're all here like we're incredibly
proud of him. uh the amount of work that
he's poured into himself and poured into
others, myself being part of that, uh
has been incredible to watch. Um I was
so excited to hear of him being named
the Walder Payton Man of the Year, but I
was not the least bit surprised by it.
And so for any of you that heard, you
know, his speech and I got you, if I
could tell you the amount of times that
I've heard I got you and like know that
he meant it, uh it meant everything. So
I was like super proud of him. So now
the purpose of uh meeting today is about
new chapters, new opportunities and uh
and also like for two terrific coaches
that I'm excited for you guys to meet.
Um we talked to a number of impressive
candidates uh and going through this
process both in and out of house and
with David and Dante uh man I I I felt
their vision um right away and the
energy they have for it. Um, I know we
made talk of uh two firsttime
coordinators, but I also uh recognize
that everybody needs their first stop.
And I really feel uh like we're going to
set them up to succeed in in every way.
And I also feel really strongly about
the staff uh that is here to support
them in that way and surround them. So,
give you a couple of those updates. Uh
on offense, Darnell Stapleton will coach
the offensive line. Uh DJ Williams we
hired as quarterback coach and Wes
Welker will also be somebody that'll
have a role on offense this year after
being on the defensive and special team
side in 25. Uh defensively we hired Eric
Henderson as the defensive line coach
reassigning Daryl Tap to assistant Dline
and we're pumped that he's here. And
then we also promoted William Gay uh to
cornerback's coach. So, after the
absolute longest open in uh the last two
years, I am uh more than glad to uh to
kick it into you guys and and let's get
down.
>> Why did you want to make change on
>> Yeah, changes are hard. You know, as
you're going through, you build these
relationships that are strong, John,
with people and players. And so when
there's time for change, those are
difficult conversations, discussions,
but at the end, you just keep going
back. What's the best thing for the team
moving forward? What's the best thing
for them? And so if I put it into those
spaces, what do we need to do moving
forward? What things need to change? And
how would we go about that? Then you
look at it from that lens. And that's
certainly what I had to do because it's
a difficult part of it. You build bonds
um with coaches and with players. And so
when you move on from them, uh, it's
challenging, but that's also I recognize
the seat that I'm in that put us in the
very best spot that we can do those.
>> And how much of that was it shaped by,
you know, just you want to take the
offense in a different direction than
maybe what matched up with what Cliff
wanted to do?
>> Yeah. And so those are uh, you know,
conversations we have all year long
about where it goes. And, uh, like I've
got like tons of respect for both Cliff
and for Joe, what they do, how they, you
know, go about it. These guys worked
incredibly hard, you know, over the two
years here. So, I thought it was time
for change, a new vision of how we'd
want to go about it. John, um, and so
that's what we did.
>> At what point in the season did you know
that, okay, maybe we need to try
something new going forward.
>> Yeah, this was a difficult one all the
way through. Um, season wise, you know,
up, down, it started that way. Good
game, bad game, good game, bad game,
long slide in the middle of it. So when
you're assessing everything, um you want
to look first, what do I need to do
differently? How do I go about changing
it? And so um it's constant assessment
to say where we're at, how we do things,
but ultimately when you're in the week
to week of it, you guys are here with me
every week thinking about the game and
how we go about winning it. Um at the
end is when it comes, you know, to light
the most.
>> And what gives you the confidence that
David Bells is ready for this um as a
play caller? Yeah, I know he hasn't been
coaching a long time, but he has, you
know, obviously when you're backup
quarterback at different things, you had
different experiences much like a
younger coach coming up. But I can also
like speak from experience um that you
know when you haven't called plays like
you've been waiting for it, you've been
doing it and in the practices you'll
probably find some spaces where do we go
to have more call it periods to go but u
we'll be really intentional about that.
um you know some of the benefits of me
going through this experience you know
as a head coach for the second time I
learned some lessons to say all right
when there's you know talented space and
you can find that certainly going
through Atlanta and some of the coaches
that were part of that staff um you know
have we done things different you might
have so like I think what you want to
find out from yourself is are you
growing are you learning and uh like
this guy's absolutely ready to go attack
and so it was it was uh evident to see
do that, but when you're around somebody
a lot, you know that, too.
>> Dan, with Dante, um, everybody's their
own man and they're going to bring their
own stuff, but what do you anticipate
he will bring from the Vikings with
regards to scheme 43 versus 34 blitz?
Yeah.
>> Blit man zone combinations.
>> Yeah. I uh
going through the the hiring process um
you know had a chance to visit with
Brian also with Donte and so from a
scheme standpoint you learn a lot in
these experiences DA because um veteran
coaches this system that system how to
go about it um much like anything the
first thing I asked him to do when we
got here I want you to look at the
players but without talking to me first
I wanted you to have your own vision so
there wasn't a bias he can do this he
can do that and let's find what they can
do best. And when I'm talking to him,
he's like the calm in the storm. I like
that about Dante. I felt the teaching
and what they can do, but we're also
going to put people in the spots, you
know, of what they can do best. And that
to me um really hit the the main cord,
DA, about what we're looking for, how we
feature players as opposed to can do
this or can't do that. Let's start with
like what they can be exceptional at and
then find other ways to utilize them.
And so pressuring and that package like
that's definitely a part of it. Um but
I'm excited, you know, for these guys to
go through it and learn it and u and
build it together.
>> At the end of the season, you had
indicated that whoever you hired would
probably be somebody that had done this
before.
>> Yep.
>> He has not done it in the at the NFL
level before. So how did he kind of
>> overcome that
>> desire of yours?
>> Yeah, that's good. Um,
I think when you're going through the
whole process, you're looking at those
strengths of where it is, where would my
time and attention go, knowing, all
right, what's going to be different
offensively, what would be different
defensively. I'm glad it went through a
lengthy process to be honest with you,
DA, because it forced me into some
spaces to look and what could be
different and what could be better. And
so Dante was one of those people that
you meet, you're like, "All right, I get
it." and I connected with him instantly
about a vision for defense and how you
would play, the ability to create
takeaways, the ability to have
disguises. And so I felt alignment even
before we got to know each other well.
We've all had those experiences like you
meet somebody, you just hit it off. I
think from a football standpoint, we we
hit it off quickly. And then that's what
made the difference to me knowing that
uh there was excellent veteran coaches
and guys who didn't have as much
experience but just weighing it through
it all and I came back to him time and
time again of just the teaching uh the
football acumen and what we were looking
for and it just really fit what we
needed.
>> Coach, when looking at hiring David
Blau, how important was it for you guys
to have a sense of continuity when
considering Jaden's development and
those other guys on the offense? Yeah,
Jaden's a big part of our thinking and
in all the things that we do. He wasn't
a part of the staff selection, but like
he drives a lot of the thinking and how
we can feature him and where it goes.
And so, um, having the ability to
connect with him, um, that's certainly a
big deal for us. Um, you know, David
amongst others in the offensive staff
have had big roles here with Jaden and,
um, it wasn't the deciding factor, but
it certainly was a good factor. And
you'd mentioned looking at unique skill
sets, unique unique abilities that new
coaches can bring in. What are those
unique skill sets that your two new
coordinators bring?
>> I think fresh eyes is the first thing
about there's a an element that goes
into new scheme, new ideas that man, it
ratches everything up quickly, uh, about
how you could go and put a different
lens on some things. And there's a lot
of excitement that goes with that. And
I'm excited for everyone, you know, in
the fall when we unveil how we want to
play that play style that it comes
across clearly for everyone. But um
different for Dante being, you know,
outside of the organization, I wanted
him to have fresh eyes on just about
everything that he could. So it wasn't
anybody, hey, this guy can do this, this
guy can do that. I can remember going
through that experience of going to
other organizations and said, just give
me a couple days, man. let me just dig
in, see what we have, and then I can
best then give you a picture of where we
are and what we need, you know, moving
forward. And so, it's really the first
step into an off season, then it gets
into free agency, your own team, the
others, then into the draft process. So,
that first step, you know, I feel like
now the momentum starts to really take
hold. It's a very important process,
much like selecting a player when you're
selecting a coach. uh they have such a
big role as play callers with an
organization and I think you can see
this year alone just the amount of
changes offense coordinators, defense
coordinators and we're a part of that
but it also goes to show you um you know
that importance and what can be done in
those spaces.
>> Dan with the DJ hire obviously a cool
story right off the bat with father and
son here uh in the building but what did
you what did you like about DJ what he
did in Atlanta? Did Doug have any
influence over the
>> Yeah, he um I'll tell you some good
stories on these. Um I've known DJ for a
while. Um dating back to times in
Atlanta. He was in New Orleans, so I had
a chance to initially get to know him
then. Um and he's always been somebody
that I've kind of kept my eye on about
what he's doing and where he's at. And
so had a chance to also visit with
Raheem about, you know, where he was and
and his growth there. and it just came
across so strongly, you know, to
everybody that I spoke with about him,
uh, about what he's doing and where he's
headed and the influence that he has.
Um, I didn't involve Doug at all. And,
um, like quite honestly, I was like
first nervous to even bring it up to
say, "What if he doesn't get it and how
would that go?" And I'm like so glad I
didn't listen to that response because I
remember getting off the the Zoom the
first time. And I said, "Holy man.
He was excellent." And so another we
interviewed, you know, some more people
and I went down to Doug's office. Hey,
man, we hired a quarterback coach. And I
think you know him. And so it was a very
cool moment um about that. But he and I
didn't discuss uh him going I'm certain
he was a good recruiter on the other
side of it. But um you it was it was a
cool thing, but you know it was almost I
just I wanted the separation, not the
connection. I knew that part would take
care of itself.
Hey, good afternoon, coach.
>> Good afternoon.
>> Um, just want to clarify something with
your external candidates. Um, did you
solicit or did any of them offer uh ex
their kind of you on your roster during
the interview process?
>> Um, some did. Um, more solicit. Hey,
what do you know? What do you think?
Where are you? Um,
my experience has been when you're with
another club and even if you're at the
end of the year and playing, you know
much about the team you're with or if
you've played against us, you know the
other side of the ball. In other words,
an offense coordinator may know more
about our defense or vice versa. So,
that part didn't come into like big
discussions about it. It was more about
how would we feature the players? What
are we looking for? Knowing that that
part can change, you know, as you're
going through it. But um it wasn't like
a driving factor, but oftentimes a
person who's a position coach becoming a
coordinator or coordinator or even a
head coach for that matter like for the
last however long they were dialed in on
their own team. And so you don't spend a
lot of time outside, but may put some
tape on as you're going through the
process and discuss some players. Same
thing with their side. Um and then as
you get here, then that changes, you
know, from free agency who's here. But I
really like for the player to have I
mean excuse me for the new coach to have
a their own fresh eyes on something and
that way we can have a better discussion
without any bias from he can do this, he
can do that. I'd much prefer it to go
the other way to man tell me your
thoughts after watching it, not you know
what you may have remembered of playing
against him a previous time.
>> And obviously all along the way we're
going to judge success or failure of of
the the staff moves that have been made.
and
>> hopefully next February we're having a
conversation with you on the success or
failure of this app as well. But for
you, where's the 50 meter target for
these new coordinators? What's the next
benchmark you're looking for them to hit
successfully?
>> Yeah, first thing um their vision, you
know, amongst to the staff now that that
part's here and so the vision comes from
me through the coordinators to the
assistant coaches and how do we make
that come to light? The first thing that
is up for us is to assist, you know,
Adam and his staff from a personnel side
of grading our own players, grading the
free agents that are there. Then we go
through the next step of doing that
along with, you know, the draft process.
But really, it's laying down the
foundation. Right now, the coaches are
working hard just on the systems. How do
we communicate it? The one good thing
that can come, not one, many of the good
things that can come is you're building
it from the ground up. So everyone here
is on the same exact page of how we're
doing it, what it's called, why it's
called, and you make those kind of
tweaks now, and everybody, you know,
who's in that room, know those why we
called this this, you know, here's the
reason why, and so that doesn't happen
very often, and we're going to take
great advantage of that.
>> Hey Dan, good to see you. Uh you
>> I know you just said Jaden didn't have
any impact on on the staff changes, but
I'm curious if you had any sort of
conversation with Jaden about moving on
from Cliff and that eventually promoting
David and what that conversation was
like and why maybe Jaden feels
comfortable that David was promoted.
>> Yeah. When I said he wasn't involved, I
should clarify. I also wanted to make
sure I was also filling him in so he
didn't hear externally, you know, what
and why. And we've got a good
relationship in that way. So, I wanted
him to hear from me before he heard from
anyone else, you know, what we were
doing and why we were doing it. And then
the same thing on the hiring process of
who and why. Um, and so those are
important things that that I did want to
have those conversations with with him.
Um, he puts a lot into it as you guys
all know from being around him and so I
love getting his feedback. I love
engaging with him. But as far as the
vision of it, you know, that had to come
from me. Then with David and Dante,
obviously two different people, two
different coaches, but is there a common
thread that both of them have that
really kind of stood out to you uh in
this process? I think you'll find being
around them like the energy for teaching
u about what that is the ability to
articulate that to everyone when I did
my I know so much about David but when I
did so much research with Donte about
the other players he's coached you know
and their feedback about what their
position coach was like it was
remarkable you know about his connection
his teachability the way he you know put
belief into people to help raise their
game up and that hadn't just been from
one player, you know, that was from a
number of players. So, those are the
type of things, you know, from a
leadership standpoint that you want to
hear about developing players, making an
impact, you know, finding ways to teach
it where it can be clear and concise and
high standards and accountability. And
when you hear players, you know, talk
that way about their position, coach,
um, that's a big deal. David differently
like his office was right near mine so
you know almost on a regular basis we're
in talking through things and ideas and
u there's some strong coaches here on
our staff to also support that vision of
how we're going to do it and so I'd say
that's the common thread these guys have
like real energy for teaching and a real
vision of what it should look like and
so I think those are the two common
threads
>> hey Dan you've talked about your vision
and it comes from you down to the
coordinators what is your vision for the
offense and and kind of what's your role
in implementing that vision for the
offense?
>> Yeah. And it'll look different some JP
in some ways as we're still kind of
building some of the things together,
but this is going to be like an
aggressive balanced attack, but like
that we'll probably have more under
center than we have in the past. Um
that's also for run action and play
passes to generate explosive plays. And
so we're going to try to feature every
part of Jaden in the way that makes him
unique and special. Um, but also the the
run action and the runs and the play
action game that goes with it. Um, those
are all things to generate explosive
plays. I think as like David was
speaking on earlier, when we're here a
year from now and we talk about the
generating the explosive plays, um,
those are a few of the things that's
going to come to mind when we're talking
about our offense.
>> And then just some clarification on Wes
Welker. Last year the role was kind of
nebulous. Is he on the offensive
coaching staff now?
>> He is. Yep. Last year he was um
supported the defensive side and also
when um he stepped in for Brian
Schneider. Um so Brian's still battling
through, you know, cancer and surgeries
and things that go along with that. And
so Wes stepped into that spot um with
Larry, you know, in an instant, but also
helped on the defensive side on some
different things. So this season, uh,
Wes will have a role with the offensive
side,
>> but not like a assistant receivers's
coach or something.
>> Correct. He's going to be on like as we
call him an offensive assistant, but
we're still working through a little bit
JP, but he'll have a a significant role
for us for sure.
>> On Dante, um, you know, what are you
hoping he brings to the younger players
like Trey Amos and Mike Se still, you
know, as they're going from one
defensive coordinator to another early
in their career? Yeah, I think clarity
and standards for the system. That's
number one. How can they help them reach
their best? And uh you're talking about
two uh incredible ones with those two at
corner. And so the value of that
position alone like speaks to it. And
like I'm very excited to meet with both
of them, what they can see, how they can
add to it. And Dante being like that's
his background. Um like that's a really
big deal for those two.
>> And speaking of Dante's background, he
has a background in the DMV. Were you
guys aware of that um in the hiring
process and was there like a glimmer in
his eyes when he first got on those
calls? I think just knowing that like
you know has a history you know here of
following the team and like went to
elementary school like not far from the
stadium and so knowing his background
here and then going to McNamera and um
you know first at Temple and then uh
back in the DMV it just like
you know it's a big deal and uh you know
for him personally and um but it's not a
deciding factor at all but I think um as
a storyline it's very cool for a guy
who's put in the in his news uh in a
very significant way in our profession.
Uh seems fitting that it should be a
place where you know he grew up loving
football.
>> With the two first time coordinators,
how important is kind of the support
staff and the other coaches in terms of
helping them along uh as they call plays
for the first time? And I guess kind of
for you, how will things change with the
way that you step in with both offense
and defense?
>> Yeah, I'm going to just try to create as
much support as I can. Um, I'll probably
include more play it, you know, times
during OTAAS and during training camp
just for that purpose and all of us
functioning together. Um, and that'll be
like, you know, at the top of it to get
them there's not like in-game
experience, but as close as we can
simulate to that as we can. Oftentimes,
you'd see all of us with practice
scripts and it's already here. And so,
there'll be times when those won't
apply. You know, we're going to call it
down in distance moving the ball and get
into those spaces. And so you do that on
film on your own, you do that on the
field and we're just going to do that.
But we do have a, you know, like I said,
an excellent staff to help support these
guys and set them up for success.
>> And then what went into moving on from
Bobby Johnson and then kind of what are
you hoping that you see from Darnell
Stapleton as he steps in on
>> I think um you know being around Darnell
over the last two years. Um he actually
interned with us as a Bill Walsh fellow
years back. Um he had like DJ had always
been somebody you know on the radar and
so to see his development over the last
two years um I knew that he was ready
for you know a significant role. He
worked closely with Bobby and Shane Tob
who were here obviously you know with
the other members of the offensive
staff. Um so it was really just you know
like a new vision of how we want to go
do it. Um that's really what it came
down to.
Hey Dan, obviously being around David
Blah the last few years, you gotten a
feel for how he understands offense, but
there's a difference between scheme and
the play calling because play calling is
under the pressure. How do you how do
you know that a guy can do that? You go
through any kind of simulations and
advance like how do you know that they
can do it under the pressure?
>> Yep. You do that, Ben. And u certainly
playing quarterback in the National
Football League helps, you know, into
that space. you're not calling your own
plays like back in the old days maybe in
the huddles, you know, that some of the
guys did, but um there's obviously lots
of training that goes into that and you
want to simulate just like you had said
with video in the games, but David has a
very clear vision of what and how um
that it's going to look and play out.
That was very evident, you know, in our
interview with him. And um going into
it, we're just going to give him the
best support we can. been like maybe
less than I initially thought of how
many calllets and those kind of thing we
need. But um as far as the leading and
the calling um those two go hand inand
but the leading part that I've seen so
far um it's all tracking that you and
everything you'd like it to be.
>> And with Dante possible collectively we
didn't get this in reporting but he he
wasn't part of the original names that
you guys interviewed. He came in later
as part of the interview process. Um he
was later to that but his name was
certainly part of that. Yeah. Part of a
group that we spoke to. I was pretty
extensive um in the group that I spoke
with.
>> I was wondering I guess why wasn't he up
there at the top and then was it just
the one meeting and like that that you
guys had that led to them?
>> He had two meetings but um yes he was
like certainly part of that but I was
you know going through a whole process.
I hadn't known him before. So I visited
with some people um but he was always
somebody that um was on the list to
visit with and where we're at and so um
it wasn't like uh you know he was down
here ranking. I don't I don't try to
rank before. I think you can get
yourself like in a bias if you do that
too often. So like I go through a rubric
of these are the questions, these are
where you go and how you can go through
it and then after then you can put that
together. So um it was really
impressive, you know, when I got
together with him on that.
>> Got time for three more.
>> Hey coach. Um, so I think at one point
in the season, toward the end of the
season, you mentioned um
this being one of the toughest years or
last year being one of the toughest
years of of your coaching career. So
what have you said, okay, this these are
the things I need to do differently
going forward?
>> Yeah, like uh full stop 25. All right, I
had to do that first. Like enough uh
beating myself up, others in that way.
And so, uh, the energy, the swagger that
we create, the standards that we want to
do for me, Kenny, it always starts first
like with practice and like the speed,
the effort, the execution of that. Um,
the locker room is a strong one. Guys
supported one another. We kind of spoke
on that so so much in a tough year. Um,
but I think just kind of like I want to
recapture that energy of that swagger of
how we want to play, the style, the
attitude of it, and I'm certain we can
do that. Uh you've heard me also say
like building a championship program
this season. I'm I'm
I'm taking the lessons. I'm moving them
forward, but it's also staying there. Uh
I'm not carrying over the things that
sucked and you know weren't part of how
we want to do business. So there's a lot
of energy that's going forward today
with the coaches and so as we're moving
forward when the players get here like
they'll be a part of that too. But I'm
ready for that process to be fully
underway.
Hey coach, um now that you've got the
coaches in place now and you look at
this team overall, what are the next
things that are glaring at you that you
say this is the next step?
>> Yeah, this just kind of completing the
first one right now, Donna, of bringing
everybody together, their connection of
how it's going to go. Um merging the
vision of what we have to what we also
want to add to the roster. And so Adam
and I have obviously lots of discussions
about the team and where we're going,
but free agency is the first one. And so
we'll have some meetings coming up
shortly. Uh the coaches were each
assigned some players and areas, they
grade them, how would they fit, what
would that look like? And so we do that
offensively, defensively before even
going to the combine. So after this part
in concert with like looking at the
personnel, putting the systems together
offensively and defensively and then
adding those pieces to it from the free
agency both from other clubs and ones
from our club, you know, say, okay, why
back? What would they roll? What would
it be?
>> And going back to and going back to
coach Jones, you said that he had his
vision and you have your vision and
you've been a play caller before. How
does it all come together where you're
speaking the same language? Yeah. And I
was wanted to be very clear with him on
that that this would be his system. I
think it's hard to think for someone
else. And so I wanted to make sure like
coming here he wouldn't have to my
system learn it this there. I said like
you're coming here to install it, man.
And uh I'm going to be here to support
you, give you insight um when you want
it. But putting that system together um
it's funny actually. I going through the
whole process with him Donna was
exciting for me too. Um, I like that the
learning can be different and what needs
to be different and what can be better.
And so those were things that that fired
me up. But, uh, ultimately like we're
putting in a new system and it's going
to start with his vision, with his
terminology, the wording that we use,
the communication that we say, and uh,
that's how it has to be. Uh, I think
it's difficult for someone else to come
in and think like someone else. I want
him to man be able to fully express, you
know, how he wants to coach it. And that
was important for me to share with him.
All right. Thanks.
>> All right. Thanks everybody. You guys
have a good one.
Tell